Chapter 130. The hat.
And now that at the proper time and place, after so long and wide a
preliminary cruise, Ahab, all other whailing waters swept, seemed to have
chased his foe into an ocean fold to slay him the more securely there. Now
that he found himself hard by the very latitude and longitude where his
tormenting wound had been inflicted, now that a vessel had been spoken, which on
the very day preceding had actually encountered Moby Dick, and now that all
his successive meetings with various ships contrastingly concurred to show
the demonic indifference with which the white whale tore his hunters, whether
sinning or sinned against, now it was that there lurked to something in the
old man's eyes, which it was hardly sufferable for feeble souls to see. As
the unsetting polar star, which through the live arctic six months night
sustains its piercing, steady central gaze, so Ahab's purpose now fixedly
gleamed down upon the constant midnight of the gloomy crew. It doineered above
them so that all their boings, doubts, misgivings, fears were fained to hide
beneath their souls, and not sprout forth a single spear or leaf.
In this foreshadowing interval, too, all humor forced or natural, vanished. Stub
no more strove to raise a smile.
Starbucks no more strove to check one.
Alike joy and sorrow, hope and fear, seemed ground to finest dust, and
powdered for the time in the clamped mortar of Ahab's iron soul. Like
machines, they dumbly moved about the deck, ever conscious that the old man's
desperate eye was on them.
But did you deeply scan him in his more secret confidential hours when he
thought no glance but one was on him?
Then you would have seen that even as Ahab's eyes so awed the cruise, the
inscrable Pars glance aed his, or somehow at least in some wild way at
times affected it. Such an added gliding strangeness began to invest the thin
Fidala. Now such ceaseless shuddering shook him that the men looked dubious at
him, half uncertain as it seemed whether indeed he were a mortal substance or
else a tremulous shadow cast upon the deck by some unseen being's body. And
that shadow was always hovering there.
For not by night even had Fidala ever certainly been known to slumber or go
below. He would stand still for hours, but never sat or leaned. His wan but
wondrous eyes did plainly say, "We two watchmen never rest."
Nor at any time by night or day, could the mariners now step upon the deck,
unless Ahab was before them, either standing in his pivot hole or exactly
pacing the planks between two undeviating limits, the main mast and
the mizen. or else they saw him standing in the cabin scuttle, his living foot
advanced upon the deck as if to step, his hat slouched heavily over his eyes,
so that however motionless he stood, however the days and nights were added
on, that he had not swung in his hammock, yet hidden beneath that
slouching hat, they could never tell unairringly whether, for all this, his
eyes were really closed at times, or whether he was still intently scanning
them. No matter, though he stood so in the scuttle for a whole hour on the
stretch, and the unheated night damp gathered in beads of dew upon that
stonecarved coat and hat. The clothes that night had wet the next day's
sunshine dried upon him. And so day after day, and night after night he went
no more beneath the planks. Whatever he wanted from the cabin, that thing he
sent for. He ate in the same open air, that is, his two only meals, breakfast
and dinner. Supper he never touched, nor reaped his beard, which darkly grew all
gnarled, as unearthed roots of trees blown over, which still grow idly on at
naked base, though perished in the upper verger. But though his whole life was
now become one watch on deck, and though the Parsey's mystic watch was without
intermission as his own, yet these two never seemed to speak, one man to the
other, unless at long intervals some passing, unmoment matter made it
necessary. Though such a potent spell seemed secretly to join the twain,
openly and to the aruck crew they seemed pole like a sunder. If by day they
chanced to speak one word, by night dumb men were both so far as concerned the
slightest verbal interchange. At times for longest hours, without a single
hail, they stood far parted in the starlight. Ahab in his scuttle, the
parsy by the main mast, but still fixedly gazing upon each other, as if in
the parse Ahab saw his forthrown shadow, in Ahab the parsy his abandoned substance.
And yet somehow did Ahab, in his own proper self, as daily, hourly, and every
instant commandingly revealed to his subordinates, Ahab seemed an independent
lord, the parsy but his slave. Still again both seemed yolked together, and
an unseen tyrant driving them, the lean shade siding the solid rib. For be this
parsy what he may, all rib and keel was solid Ahab.
At the first faintest glimmering of the dawn, his iron voice was heard from aft,
man the mast heads. And all through the day till after sunset and after twilight
the same voice every hour at the striking of the helmsman's bell was
heard. What do you see? Sharp. Sharp.
But when three or four days had slided by after meeting the children seeking
Rachel, and no spout had yet been seen, the monoomanic old man seemed
distrustful of his crews fidelity. At least of nearly all except the pagan
harpooners. He seemed to doubt even whether Stub and Flask might not
willingly overlook the sight he sought.
But if these suspicions were really his, he sagaciously refrain from verbally
expressing them, however his actions might seem to hint them.
I will have first sight of the whale myself, he said. I, Ahab, must have the
deloon. and with his own hands he rigged a nest of basketed bolands and sending a
handoft with a single sheaved block to secure to the main mast head he received
the two ends of the downward reeved rope and attaching one to his basket prepared
a pin for the other end in order to fasten it at the rail this done with
that end yet in his hand and standing beside the pin he looked round upon his
crew sweeping from one to the other pausing his glance long upon on Dagu
Quiqu Tashego, but shunning Fidala, and then settling his firm, relying eye upon
the chief mate, said, "Take the rope, sir. I give it into thy hands,
Starbucks." Then, arranging his person in the basket, he gave the word for them
to hoist him to his perch. Starbucks being the one who secured the rope at
last, and afterward stood near it. And thus, with one hand clinging round the
royal mast, Ahab gazed abroad upon the sea for miles and miles, ahead, a stern,
this side and that, within the wide expanded circle commanded at so great a height.
When, in working with his hands at some lofty, almost isolated place in the
rigging, which chances to afford no foothold, the sailor at sea is hoisted
up to that spot, and sustained there by the rope. Under these circumstances, its
fastened end on deck is always given in strict charge to some one man who has
the special watch of it, because in such a wilderness of running rigging, whose
various different relations aloft cannot always be infallibly discerned by what
is seen of them at the deck, and when the deck ends of these ropes are being
every few minutes cast down from the fastenings, it would be but a natural
fatality, if unprovided with a constant ent watchmen. The hoisted sailor should
by some carelessness of the crew be cast a drift and fall all swooping to the
sea. So Ahab's proceedings in this matter were not unusual. The only
strange thing about them seemed to be that Starbucks, almost the one only man
who had ever ventured to oppose him with anything in the slightest degree
approaching to decision, one of those two whose faithfulness on the lookout he
had seemed to doubt somewhat. It was strange that this was the very man he
should select for his watchmen, freely giving his whole life into such an
otherwise distrusted person's hands.
Now the first time Ahab was perched aloft air. He had been there 10 minutes,
one of those redbuild savage seahawks which so often fly incomodiously close
round the manned mast heads of whalemen in these latitudes. One of those birds
came wheeling and screaming round his head in a maze of untrackably swift
circlings. Then it darted a thousand feet straight up into the air, then
spiralized downwards and went eddying again round his head. But with his gaze
fixed upon the dim and distant horizon, Ahab seemed not to mark this wild bird.
Nor indeed would anyone else have marked it much, it being no uncommon
circumstance. Only now almost the least heedful eye seemed to see some sort of
cunning meaning in almost every sight.
Your hat. Your hat, sir. Suddenly cried the Sicilian seaman, who being posted at
the misen mast head, stood directly behind Ahab, though somewhat lower than
his level, and with a deep gulf of air dividing them. But already the sable
wing was before the old man's eyes, the long hooked bill at his head. With a
scream, the black hawk darted away with his prize.
An eagle flew thrice round Tarquin's head, removing his cap to replace it.
And thereupon Tanakquil, his wife, declared that Tarquin would be king of
Rome. But only by the replacing of the cap was that omen accounted good. Ahab's
hat was never restored. The wild hawk flew on and on with it, far in advance
of the prow, and at last disappeared, while from the point of that
disappearance a minute black spot was dimly discerned, falling from that vast
height into the sea.